

DANIEL RUIZ

DATA SCIENTIST & ML ENGINEER

Databricks, Azure, & Scrum Certified I make AI create value for your company!

DETAILS

www.danielruiz.nl daniel.rocharuiz@bocconialumni.it +31 653.398.717 Citizenship: Italian (EU) Residence: Amsterdam, NL

ABOUT ME

Daniel is here to solve your problems with AIML and MLOPS. He is a proven Data Scientist and Machine Learning Engineer with a strong background in Azure and Databricks. He has experience in Finance, Retail, Transportation, Education, Healthcare, and Energy. He has developed and productionized ML models with different architectures and has delivered E2E ML transformations. He's a team player, and he holds an Azure Expert and 4 Azure Associate certifications.

LANGUAGES

PortugueseNativeEnglishFluentItalianFluentGermanFluentDutchBeginner

EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning Engineer (Consultant), Devoteam, Amsterdam, 2022-Now

- <u>Developed models for Energy and Gas consumption forecasting</u>, and deployment_systems and processes to bring them into production. Leveraged Azure Machine Learning to make <u>customer-specific models</u>.
- Guided and oriented teams on <u>Software Engineering best practices</u> to model development (Source Control, CI/CD, MLOPS, etc.).
- Stack: AML, ADO/Git/Pipelines, Databricks, Snowflake, Linux/Bash, PyTest, Pre-Commit, Streamlit, MLfLow, PySpark, SQL, Agile/Scrum.

Machine Learning Engineer (Senior Analyst), Avanade, Hamburg, 2020-2022

- <u>Developed MLOPS systems and processes</u> for a <u>pharmaceutical</u> company, helping to <u>expedite and safeguard</u> different stages of Drug Development.
- Developed a model using <u>state-of-the-art tree algorithms</u> to input missing data on proprietary datasets, achieving 99.999% accuracy on <u>out-of-sample data</u>.
- Stack: AML, ADO/Git/Pipelines, Databricks, Linux/Bash, Docker, PyTest, MissingPy, TensorFlow, MLflow, PySpark, Scikit-Learn, SQL, Agile/Scrum.

Cloud Migration Consultant, NDA (Healthtech), Toronto, Fall 2020

- <u>Mapped the cloud migration process</u> of a high-profile Canadian tech company, interviewing multiple teams and stakeholders involved in the process.
- <u>Identified bottlenecks and low-hanging fruits</u> that could expedite the migration process, as well as <u>risks</u>. This was a semester-long interaction as part of an MBA class at Rotman School of Commerce, in Toronto.
- Stack: LucidChart, Qualitative Interviewing, Process Mining, MS Office.

CLM Graduate Intern, Deutsche Bank, Frankfurt, Summer 2019

- Supported <u>CLM, AML, and KYC</u> activities to meet regulatory demands.
- Participated in multiple activities in Commercial Banking Operations, Tech, and Analytics.
- Stack: Microsoft Office, Excel, Proprietary Software.

Pricing Analyst, Kroton, São Paulo, Summer and Fall 2018

- Used <u>regression models</u> to <u>analyze competition</u> and provide insight to the pricing strategy of 4k new products and readjust existing products. Kroton has circa <u>1 million students</u> affected by pricing decisions.
- <u>Automated the daily reporting and emailing</u> of targets, minimizing human inputs and reducing update time by 90%.
- Stack: Microsoft Office, Excel VBA, Power BI, Agile/Scrum.

Equity Research Intern, Morgan Stanley, São Paulo, 2017

- <u>Developed and updated financial and statistical models</u> and performed fundamental analysis and valuation of over 40 companies in Aviation, Infrastructure, Retail, and Pharma sectors. Supported two IPOs.
- Prepared actionable reports and participated in calls with C-level executives.
- Automated financial reports using Eikon & VBA, reducing update time by 90%.
- Stack: Microsoft Office, Excel VBA, Bloomberg, Thomson Reuters Eikon.

GENERAL SKILLS

Data Science, Modelling, NLP, Machine Learning, Software Engineering, MLOPS, Data Visualization, Data Engineering, Scrum/Agile, DevOps, Source Control, Teamwork, Rapid Learning.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Platforms	Airflow, Anaconda, Azure, AWS, Databricks, GitHub, Jira, Snowflake
Programming	Python, SQL, Linux/Bash, Stata, R, Octave, Power Bl, Kubernetes, Docker, APIs, Git
Python	Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib, MissingPy, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Streamlit, etc
Machine	Azure Machine
Learning	Learning, PyTorch, PySpark, TensorFlow, AML, Scikit-Learn, Jupyter, Forecasting, NLP, AutoML
Others	Terraform/ARM, Scrum/Agile

HOBBIES AND INTERESTS

Data & AI, Italian literature, museums, outdoor sports, hiking, running (10km and 21km), travelling, and meeting friends.

Offshore Client Services Intern | Itaú Asset Management | São Paulo | 2015

- Elaborated presentations and revised materials specific to international investors for both Fixed and Variable Income strategies; often, collected data directly from Bloomberg terminals.
- Stack: Microsoft Office, Excel VBA, Bloomberg.

EDUCATION

MSc in Data Science and Business Analytics, Bocconi University, 2018-2020

- E2E design and development of a program that mined over six million tweets, performed noisy-label sentiment analysis (NLP), and analyzed stock performance (ML).
- Academic exchange at the University of Toronto (Canada), partaking MBA classes of Analytics, Finance, and Health Consulting.

BSc in Economics, University of São Paulo, 2014-2017

- Extremely heavy load of Econometrics (including Time-Series) and Statistics.
- Analyzed over 200 million stock orders from São Paulo Stock Exchange, looking for patterns of stock manipulation and market failures.
- Academic exchange at Bocconi University (Italy).

Summer Course in International Economics, LSE, 2016

• Studied models of international trade and finance, heavily based on noarbitrage, microeconomic equilibrium, and partial differential equations.

CERTIFICATIONS

CFA Institute

• CFA ESG: Certificate in ESG Investing

Databricks

- ML I: Databricks Machine Learning Associate
- MLII: Databricks Machine Learning Professional

Microsoft

- AZ400: Azure DevOps Engineer Expert
- AZ204: Azure Developer Associate
- Al102: Azure Al Engineer Associate
- DP203: Azure Data Engineer Associate
- DP100: Azure Data Scientist Associate

Scrum.org

- PSM II: Professional Scrum Master II
- PSM I: Professional Scrum Master I